<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>leblancfg.com - Vim</title><link href="https://leblancfg.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://leblancfg.com/feeds/vim.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://leblancfg.com/</id><updated>2023-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><subtitle>Data Science, Geospatial Python, Space Stuff</subtitle><entry><title>TIL: NERDTree Bookmarks</title><link href="https://leblancfg.com/til-nerdtree-bookmarks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>François Leblanc</name></author><id>tag:leblancfg.com,2023-03-22:/til-nerdtree-bookmarks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NERDTree Bookmarks is a plugin that allows you to bookmark files and directories in NERDTree.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a developer, you probably spend a lot of time navigating through the directories of your project. Whether you're looking for a specific file, checking your tests, or exploring a new feature, it can be time-consuming to constantly type in the same directory paths. Fortunately, I just discovered a way to make this faster in a Vim plug-in I've been using for years called NERDTree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bookmarks allow you to save your most frequently used directories and easily navigate to them with just a few keystrokes. Unlike regular bookmarks in your web browser, NERDTree bookmarks are saved to a file on your computer, so they work across multiple sessions and computer restarts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of repetitively opening and closing the same directories when moving around, you can just bookmark them and quickly jump to them whenever you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Creating a New Bookmark&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following commands are only accessible when your cursor is in a NERDTree pane. If you're not seeing the command show up, this might be why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a new bookmark, simply navigate to the directory you want to save in NERDTree, and press &lt;code&gt;:Bookmark&lt;/code&gt; to assign a shortcut to that bookmark. For example, to save a bookmark in the &lt;code&gt;tests/&lt;/code&gt; folder, place your cursor on top, press &lt;code&gt;:Bookmark&lt;/code&gt;, and you will then be able to see this new bookmark within your NERDTree pane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default there is no shortcut assigned to the bookmark, but a simple &lt;code&gt;:Bo&amp;lt;Tab&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; should suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of NERDTree bookmark called &amp;quot;output&amp;quot;" src="img/NERDTree_bookmark.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Jumping to an Existing Bookmark&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To jump to an existing bookmark, you'll need to use the &lt;code&gt;:OpenBookmark &amp;lt;BOOKMARK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; command. Again, using tab completion typing e.g. &lt;code&gt;:OpenBookmark output&lt;/code&gt; ends up being a quick &lt;code&gt;:Op&amp;lt;Tab&amp;gt; o&amp;lt;Tab&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Try it for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Listing and Editing Bookmarks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can list and edit all your existing bookmarks by typing &lt;code&gt;:EditBookmarks&lt;/code&gt; in NERDTree. This will display a list of all your bookmarks and their corresponding shortcuts, which can be edited, deleted, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, NERDTree bookmarks are a powerful feature that can save you a lot of time and make your development workflow more efficient. By creating and managing your bookmarks, you can quickly navigate through your project and focus on what really matters - writing great code!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Vim"></category><category term="vim"></category><category term="nerdtree"></category><category term="bookmarks"></category></entry></feed>